[SPEAKER_02]
Things were just starting to look up for Jorge when the thing with the TV happened.
He just moved to a new town, started his life over, found some work, got a place.
[SPEAKER_02]
Yours is searching around in vagueness, were endless.
[SPEAKER_03]
It's going well. Like the way that I'm procrastinating now is by like doing work, you know?
you know, I'm coming into my own. Like I feel good. I'm paying
[SPEAKER_03]
Bill's relatively on time.
[SPEAKER_02]
I moved to New York City, which was scary, and lucked into an apartment that real New Yorkers told him was a find, a little studio in the East Village, one room, good location, cheap.
And then one night he's sitting at his table, watching the bachelorette on TV.
[SPEAKER_02]
And it's the episode where the bachelorette has whittled it down to four guys that she's going to pick one from eventually.
and she's in New York City visiting one of the potentials.
[SPEAKER_03]
And, you know, so he goes out to dinner with his with his family and they're, you know, they eat and, you know, they've got the shifty-eyed sister and, you know, like everybody's family acts the exact same way, you know?
and then and then they get in the limousine and
[SPEAKER_03]
They they decide to go back to his apartment.
Now like, now I'm
[SPEAKER_03]
Now I'm on the I'm on the edge of my seat.
you know, I just moved I moved to New York, like it's an enormous city and
[SPEAKER_03]
I would be so excited if I could recognize us through it. I would be so excited. It would just make me so happy.
And so I'm totally I'm totally sad.
[SPEAKER_00]
Error: Invalid operation: The `response.text` quick accessor requires the response to contain a valid `Part`, but none were returned. The candidate's [finish_reason](https://ai.google.dev/api/generate-content#finishreason) is 1.
[SPEAKER_03]
So they they get out of the limo and and he hugs her in the street.
And they painted.
[SPEAKER_03]
and they show a building, they show an army.
And it's my honor.
[SPEAKER_03]
It's your building. It's my building. It's the awning to my building.
It says the address, it says the street, it's, you know, it's possibly the only place in New York I actually know.
[SPEAKER_03]
And then they and then he opens the door and she comes in and it's my lobby, you know? There's my lobby. There's the row of mailboxes, you know? And I'm I'm just like, I'm I'm out of my chair and I'm can't talk. I'm like,
you know, like pointing at the TV.
[SPEAKER_02]
If it were me, I would think like, are they here right now? Like in the building?
[SPEAKER_03]
you
You're too smart. I mean, I was, you know, I was, I couldn't think. I was just like
[SPEAKER_03]
you know. It was, you know what I mean? I was just like, it was, you know, I was just flabbergast. It just couldn't be happening, you know?
[SPEAKER_02]
Why doesn't take the elevator up to the fourth floor? Jorge lives on the fifth.
They walked down the hallway to the
[SPEAKER_02]
And then Jorge realizes something else.
[SPEAKER_03]
You know, he doesn't just live in the city as me. He doesn't live on the same street as me. He doesn't just live in the same building as me. He basically lives in my apartment.
He lives in the exact same apartment. It's the exact same layout.
[SPEAKER_02]
So wait, so like, so the camera goes inside this apartment and you see
your apartment basically.
[SPEAKER_03]
a much better version of my apartment.
his is much better.
[SPEAKER_03]
the walls are lighter
The place is cleaner, the furniture is nicer. He has a half wall.
[SPEAKER_03]
He's got a half wall. A half wall with a brick
[SPEAKER_02]
This is a test broadcast.
[SPEAKER_03]
It's like, it's like, it's like drywall, you know?
But it but it seems like it has like some sort of like counter top kind of thing on it.
[SPEAKER_02]
And at that moment, Jorge gets this flash.
He is not really doing all that well.
[SPEAKER_02]
This apartment is a kind of dump compared to this guy who's on TV.
Plus, he's watching Trista Ren, the Bachelorette on TV, looking uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_02]
in his apartment on National TV.
In fact, she bails on the guy.
[SPEAKER_03]
she leaves the apartment and they cut to like that that that that head-on interview, you know, and she's just looking into the camera and she says,
I've I've dated guys with with really bad apartments before.
[SPEAKER_03]
I I can't judge him on that. I have to
I have to find out why why he feels like he can live in an apartment like this.
[SPEAKER_03]
student
[SPEAKER_02]
because of the apartment
Yeah. Wait, he lost out on the Bachelorette because of the apartment? Oh, yeah. And it was your apartment?
[SPEAKER_02]
but better.
Over the next few days, it all sort of goes to hell for Jorge. He's depressed, his new life does not seem so shiny.
[SPEAKER_02]
His New York friends console him. Look, they say, the bachelorette had never seen a New York apartment before. She does not know how people here live. This means nothing.
which helps them for a while until one day.
[SPEAKER_02]
Jorge picks up the New York Post and reads.
is an article about his neighbor Todd, the guy from the Bachelorette.
[SPEAKER_02]
Getting busted with cocaine.
[SPEAKER_03]
third paragraph.
Toddman's fate on the Bachelorette was sealed the moment Ren set foot in this in his squalid Avenue A studio apartment.
[SPEAKER_03]
Do you understand the weight of that? Squalid.
squalid avenue A studio apartment
[SPEAKER_03]
So this isn't just like people from outside New York. This is the New York Post. Nobody knows New York apartments like the New York Post. These guys have been in the most squalid New York City apartments. It's squalid, you know. It's squalid, squalid, squalid.
you know, there's not there's not that many definitions for squalor.
[SPEAKER_03]
There's not many ways to look at the word squalid.
um
[SPEAKER_03]
Maybe they mean kind of hip, you know?
Hahahaha.
[SPEAKER_02]
somehow, without ever meaning to.
Jorge had the experience that a person
[SPEAKER_02]
if he actually went on to one of the reality shows and then got booted off the show.
National television came into his apartment.
[SPEAKER_02]
and then kicked them off the island.
by proxy
[SPEAKER_02]
He was like collateral damage to a reality show.
[SPEAKER_03]
you know, I I never I didn't want to be I didn't want America to judge judge me and
Tell me my apartment sucks.
[SPEAKER_03]
I didn't want I didn't want that, but
that moment when I was, you know, when when they came into my building.
[SPEAKER_03]
Nick, they opened that door and it was my apartment.
I thought I was, you know, I thought that I was hot. I thought that it was, you know,
[SPEAKER_03]
I that's, you know, and then all of a sudden
Biew biew biew.
[SPEAKER_03]
you know
What was it?
[SPEAKER_03]
You lose. You lose. You lose.
[SPEAKER_02]
deux
He says that if he hadn't just moved to New York City, if he hadn't just started this whole life, it would not have been the kick in the stomach that it was.
[SPEAKER_02]
Which brings us to today's radio program.
From WBEZ Chicago, it's This American Life. I'm Ira Glass.
[SPEAKER_02]
Today on our show
Starting from scratch.
[SPEAKER_02]
stories of people in that period of their lives when everything is up for grabs, they're starting over, everything is tenuous.
Act one.
[SPEAKER_02]
Puppy love
the business model
[SPEAKER_02]
Act two.
Making money the old fashioned way.
[SPEAKER_02]
in that ad
The story of a man, a limo driver to be exact.
[SPEAKER_02]
It begins each day from scratch with just a few bucks.
It builds into
[SPEAKER_02]
thousands or tens of thousands by the end of the day.
Actually
[SPEAKER_02]
the first starting from scratch
In that act Jonathan Goldstein revisits a possibly familiar tale.
[SPEAKER_02]
of a man, a woman, a garden, and a snake. Stay with me.
At one, puppy love the business model.
[SPEAKER_02]
Okay, you know there are mom and pop grocery stores, mom and pop newspapers.
But could you throw everything away, change your life, start your life over?
[SPEAKER_02]
and create a mom and pop cable network.
Molly Fitzsimmons' own father tried, and she has the answer.
[SPEAKER_01]
Some people's fathers quit their jobs and become teachers.
Some may be retired early and start a new hobby like model building.
[SPEAKER_01]
My father, after turning over the reigns of the business he'd owned and operated for 25 years, started a cable channel.
from scratch
[SPEAKER_01]
It was February 1995 and he was looking for something new to do, but he didn't know what.
Then came the OJ trial.
[SPEAKER_01]
He just had back surgery and the day they sent him home for bed rest happened to be the day that the trial began.
During the long breaks in the action, he would flip through the channels.
[SPEAKER_00]
there was so much downtime.
in the trial, I had a chance to see everything that was on television.
[SPEAKER_00]
all day long
for weeks
[SPEAKER_01]
You mean you just surfed online?
[SPEAKER_00]
The slow points in the trial were most of the day.
And I spent the time surfing around.
[SPEAKER_00]
daytime television and seeing what it was.
[SPEAKER_01]
What it was was mostly soap operas, talk shows, reruns, game shows, things that my father had no interest in.
My father is a problem solver, and this was a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]
So I thought, something else is necessary.
There's a need for a parking place.
[SPEAKER_00]
on television if you don't want to watch something that is there
You could have the TV set on.
[SPEAKER_00]
And it would be playing something that
didn't bother you.
[SPEAKER_00]
would hold the place until your favorite show or what you chose to watch.
[SPEAKER_01]
For my father, like for a lot of people, simply turning off the television isn't an option.
So he's stuck flipping through a bunch of shows that he hates waiting for the OJ trial to come back on when a little light bulb goes off in his head.
[SPEAKER_00]
I recalled
My wife and I
[SPEAKER_00]
walking to lunch on a Friday in downtown Cleveland, walking into a building.
The Animal Protective League had uh uh puppies.
[SPEAKER_00]
up for adoption.
and the crowd of people standing around these puppies.
[SPEAKER_00]
included
men in the in three-piece suits and women in
[SPEAKER_00]
in fancy outfits and
Shoppers
[SPEAKER_00]
moms with kids in strollers, the the UPS man.
And they stood together.
[SPEAKER_00]
smiling and chuckling and even sometimes addressing one another in the
in the in the middle of a a big city building